physical exercise specifically
resistance exercise in kids as clear as
I can say this does not stunt growth
plates lifting weights in kids will not
hurt bone menal density it will not make
them get shorter it will not fuse those
end plates any sooner or anything like
that I I can't emphasize enough how much
I want to kill the absolute hell out of
that myth we have known this answer for
a long time and somehow it continues to
persist around the world it is
absolutely and fundamentally untrue in
fact very
specifically many many studies over tens
of thousands of kids generally strength
training resistance training weight
training Plyometrics enhance bone
quality and most importantly not only
does it do it in that age window it will
last then the rest of their life
remember earlier when I said what you do
as a teenager will determine your bone
Minal density the rest of your life this
will happen as well with exercise
strength training resistance exercise
Sports and everything else like that so
these things are good for kids in
general
obviously within range I don't want you
to overuse kids don't burn them out you
can do too much physical activity like
all those things are true right what
we're talking about is responsible
exercise supervised strength training
making sure kids are playing and still
having fun and all of the necessary
caveats that should be there of course
kids can get hurt when they lift weights
of course you can do damage but in
general these things are not only okay
and safe they're incredibly productive
for short and long-term bone health I
can't be more clear on that point there
is evidence that simply being active
kids that are Physically Active think
about this in terms of a study where you
simply ask kids about how active they
are what does active mean whatever they
want it to mean okay so just being
active over 90% of studies that have
been done in this area find positive
benefits with activity and bone meral
density it doesn't matter if we're
looking at randomized control trials
intervention studies cross-sectional
longitudinal questionnaires retroactive
studies you smash them all together 90%
of them find positive associations
between more active and more mineral
density again obviously that can be
taken to an extreme where you're too
active but you get the point here right
very directly active kids between the
ages of 8 and 15 will have 10% more bone
mineral density by the time they're in
their 20s and 30s 10% more when they're
more active between age 8 and 15 so
again you're really laying the
foundation for what they're going to
deal with the rest of their life the
benefits that we see with physical
activity seem to be Exel tolerated more
specifically with sport interaction and
it's actually by a large margin
somewhere between like 10 to 16% of the
difference in bone mineral density in
kids who play sports versus those who
don't so if I were to take kids that are
generally playing sports versus kids of
the same age that are not playing sports
we would expect again a 10 to 16%
increase or greater amount of boneal
density in those kids playing sports so
keep your kids active get them playing a
lot of different sports and activities
if then on top of that as a third area
you want to add in what I call formal
exercise then that's great this is when
you're intentionally exercising
intentionally having them uh lift
weights or intentionally doing things
like that that's great but the reality
of it is I firmly believe if your kids
are active and playing again a very open
definition of sport that's probably
going to be everything that you need the
one thing I will emphasize here
is most of the research and most of the
benefit tends to come from jumping and
Landing remember Wolf's Law in order for
a bone to increase or to be stimulated
you got to place a large Demand on it
you need actual structural pounding of
the of the bone itself or you need the
muscle to be contracting at a rate where
it's really ripping on the bone not a
slow controlled contraction right so
either the weight itself has to jar up
and down and called create axial loading
on the bone to stimulate it or a muscle
or a tendon or connected tissue has to
be directly pulling on it rapidly and
aggressively so most of the studies here
are plyometric based which is further
emphasizes our Point Plyometrics
themselves are not dangerous for kids in
fact they're generally very beneficial
if you enjoyed this clip you can watch
the full episode by clicking here
[Music]